Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 December 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Has just returned from Paimboeuf where he saw as fine a ship as any in the navy. Expects to see Captain Nicholson and if the obstacles are removed, will soon finish the expedition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Thompson, Thomas. L'Orient
    Describes the ship, Duras, a great bargain but old and in sad need of repairs; discusses the advisability of purchasing her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Girandeau. B. La Rochelle
    His ship destined for Maryland or Virginia; begs Franklin to accord his captain letters of recommendation as he knows no one in that part of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Walton, George. Savannah
    Has lately returned from Congress. Sums up the successes of the American arms; general opinion that Howe's safety depends on his flight; strictness of blockade around Philadelphia where horses are being killed for food. News just received of the capture, by the Americans, of the Syren and two transports off Rhode Island. Georgia in the tolerable state of defense; plundering war carried on by their neighbors in Florida.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Guillaume Jaeger, Jean. Frankfort-on-the-Main
    Concerning a powder mill which he desires to erect according to a new plan of construction, a sketch of which he encloses; applies to Franklin, as one of the greatest philosophers and mechanics, for his advice; would offer his services to Congress were he not old and fatigued with many campaigns.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Chambrier, ------- Bedaulx née. Neufchâtel
    Her son sailed in April with the Marquis de Lafayette; begs Franklin not to lose sight of him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Hayes, W. Paris
    Writes on behalf of the orphan son of Mr. Huske whom he once served as the valet de chambre; his apprenticeship to Mr. Hooper, of Wilmington, nearly expired; begs Franklin to recommend the young man to some one of his friends in that part of the world.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 23; L.S. 2p.; Lefebure, Marquis. St. Valery sur Somme
    Very uneasy about the bark, Le Dillon, and the captain, François Lefebure, his son; she was captured on July 24th by an American and taken, it was said, to Boston; has had no further news; begs Franklin to give him some information of the matter, if possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Defleury, Bertherand. Paris
    Begging for news of the fate of M. le Chevalier Du Coudray; ties of friendship and relationship make him hope that the public rumors may not be confirmed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Wright, Patience. London
    The bearer is Mr. Geo. Searle, who has advanced the twenty guineas for her bill on Franklin, drawn for the use of Mr. Platt.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 December 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Sending a deposition made by Captain Benet, who was lately taken by the English at the entrance of the river.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Walpole, Thomas. London
    Thanking Franklin for his valuable present to his son; hopes now that he possesses an impression of Franklin's person, he will study to imitate his conduct. Misplaced confidence shown by the legislative and executive powers in the present ministers; Lord Chatham's views on this subject, as shown by his motion for a cessation of war and a recall of the troops; he and Lord Camden send their best compliments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Rolandeau, -----. Bordeaux
    Thanking Franklin for the flattering letter he has been kind enough to give him; begs that he will join to it an order for a free passage; M. Delap, at Bordeaux, the person to write to; his desires to sail at once.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Ballainvilliers, -----. Paris
    Asking Franklin to take charge of the enclosed letter to his friend, M. de la Fayette.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 24; A.L.S. 2p.; de Favarez, -----
    Use of tobacco ashes in dropsy; desires to know the dose and the method of administering it. His enthusiastic partisanship of the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Webb, Benjamin. London
    Recommending Mr. Roegler; his reputation as a scholar at the University of Leipzig.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Baudouin, ------ Secretary to M. de Sartine. Paris
    Has received the letter Franklin sent; will translate and send it to M. de Sartine by his courier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Thompson, Thomas. L'Orient
    Every matter concerning the Raleigh transacted by M. Bérard to his entire satisfaction; the port of L'Orient a safe harbor and easy of access.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Leopold, Comte Barbo. Fidesch, Hungary
    His former military services; desires to know how he can reach the headquarters of General Washington, and if, on his arrival, he will be sure to get a position as Major.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 26; L.S. 2p.; Kothkowski, Count. London
    Embarked on a Dutch ship bound for Boston with Franklin's letter of recommendation to General Washington; was taken prisoner and brought to Portsmouth; suffered all kinds of bad treatment from the English; his destitute condition; begs Franklin to write a line in his favor to Mr. Benjamin Vaughan, of London, who will then procure him the means of realizing his former intentions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 26; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lavabre and Doerner. Paris
    Enclosing a letter for Franklin from Amsterdam and asking Franklin to give the bearer the promised letter of recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Lacepède, Bernard-Germain-Etienne de La Ville-sur-Illon, comte de. Paris
    Concerning certain experiments which he invites Franklin to witness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Lambert, -----. Basle, Switzerland
    Congratulates him on the victories in America, and requests a commission in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 27; A.L.S. 3p.; De Norey, Jean Louis Destelan. Rennes
    Account of his services and request for a commission in the American navy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Arnold, George. Maycnce
    Veneration Germans have for the heroic deeds of General Arnold. Is he the son of a Mayence butcher? Was he a monk of the order of St. Francis? Arnold wrote to Mayence in 1773. Received papal dispensation recently. Thinks General Arnold is his son. A copper print of Arnold, made in London, in 1776, and sold in Mayence, confirms his belief. Others assert that General Arnold was born in New England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Requesting another letter of credit on M. Grand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 27; L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Manhcim, Pa
    Has been entirely undeceived with respect to his brother; being unable to defend him longer, is determined to give him up entirely to his own fate; apologizes profusely to Dr. Franklin and Mr. Deane for his conduct in this affair; his error founded on misinformation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Platt, Ebenezer Smith. Newgate Prison
    Thanking Franklin for relieving his sufferings; in case of an exchange, begs that he may be included therein.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Jean Bauchers and Co. Prague
    Offering their services as dealers in glass-ware asking for the usual measure of window glass in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 27; L.S. 3p.; De Bazantin, Chevalier. St. Augustine
    Still another proof of his customary bad luck; sailed for America July 18th; arrived at Charlestown; received a sum of money from the Committee of Carolina to enable him and the other members of the corps to join General Washington; captured on the way by two English frigates; held as prisoners in St. Augustine, Florida; privations and miseries; their united desire to return home; begs Franklin to narrate these facts to anyone who takes an interest in his fate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Cantini, -----. Paris
    Encloses a letter and begs Franklin to send the answer to his care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 28; A.L.S 2p.; Monézy, Frère. Bergerac
    Begs Franklin to intercede for him, a carmelite friar, with Father Gautier, in Paris, and to ask that his failings be condoned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
    Introducing Comte de Rostaing a general officer of artillery and a man of great worth. Great victories obtained in America. Reminds Franklin of his promise to give his son an introduction to the Bishop of St. Asaph.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 28; L. 2p.; Deux-Ponts, Marianne Camasse, duchesse La douairière de
    Requests a commission in the American army, for her nephew, M. de Fontevieux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Haudouin, Chevalier. Paris
    Recommending a friend who wishes to enter the American service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 28; A.L.S. 2p.; de Montels, Laroque. St. Omer
    A request to enter the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lavabre and Doerner. Paris
    Begging Franklin to send, by bearer, the letters of recommendation he promised them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Gourlade, -----. L'Orient
    Informing him that the two frigates of Congress, the Raleigh and the Alfred sailed that afternoon, accompanied by the King's frigate which had orders to render them every assistance; during their stay, neglected no opportunity of being useful to them. Arrival of Mr. Moylan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 29; A.L.S 2p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Departure of the Raleigh and Alfred, accompanied by a French sloop of war; will communicate with him later on the subject of his errand at L'Orient.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Francq, François. Montreuil
    Begging for news of his son, Antoine-Maximilien-César Le Francq, who enlisted under the American flag.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Washington, I. Le Haye
    Believes he is related to the famous general of the same name; begs Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to him containing a copy of his coat of arms; ardently desires to go over to America, should this relationship prove to be true.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 30; A.L.S. 1p.; du Marqués, Ausquer. Rennes
    He requests to enter the American army, if in no other way, as a common soldier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?] December 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Conway, Françoise-Antoinette-Jeanne Langlois du Bouchet, comtesse de. Auxerre
    Congratulating him on the late successes in America; asks if it is true that Mr. Allen has a letter for her from her husband, the General; good wishes for Franklin and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777. December ?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, William. Chaillot
    News in the London papers of the evacuation of Mud Island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December ?; A.L. 1p.; Thornton, J. London
    Delivered all the letters, except those of Lord North and Sir Grey Cooper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1p.; Adanson, M
    Sending his address and requesting that it be given to Mr. Deane.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; Mem. in 3d P. 3p.; Amabert, -----
    Requests a commission in the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [after 1780 October 13]; L. 1p.; La Rouërie, Comtesse de
    Inquiring about her son, Colonel [Charles] Armand [Marquis de la Rouerie], who was serving in the American army under General Gates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777; A.L.S. 1p.; Bancroft, Edward. Paris
    Arrival of Mr. Hodge from Dunkirk; Mr. Deane entreats Dr. Franklin to come to town immediately on business of very great importance.
  - Chevalier de Beauteville, [1778 May 24]; L.S. 3p.; Beauteville, Chevalier de
    Gives an extract from a letter written to him by Abbé d' Aydie concerning a young nobleman, M. d' Abzac, who wishes to go to America and serve under La Fayette. Asks if Franklin can give this young man a passport and a letter of recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 August]; A.L.S. 4p.; Lebègue de Presle, Achille-Guillaume
    Account of how the Board House, at Purflect, was struck by lightning and what damage was done, mostly to the roof of the building. After the accident the lightning rods on the roof were found to have a round copper knob or cap at the top, instead of being sharply pointed as recommended.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Bertier, Père Joseph Etienne
    Desiring to serve in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Bertier, Père Joseph Etienne
    Inquires if he has any news of M. de Fleury a French officer in the service of the United States.
  - to The American Commissioners., [ After 1777 May 18]; Mem. 1p.; de Brétigney, -----
    Is a captain of infantry with rank of licutenant colonel; proposes to bring to America, at his own expense, ten officers, also to fit out a troop to be commanded by these officers. M. de Beaumarchais endorses him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.]; L. 1p.; Brisson, -----
    Offers to supply Congress with flint stones for use by the American troops.
    A.E. by Franklin thanking him for his offer and promising to send it to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?] Wednesday ---; A.L.S 1p.; Carmichael, William, d. 1795
    Sends substance of Lord Chatham's motion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; Mem. in 3d P. 1p.; de Chanteclair, -----
    Request to enter the service of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S 3p.; Chaulnes, Duc de
    Has been to see Abbé Rochon who showed him an experiment in electricity with a metal jar on a glass base. Thinks he has found the explanation of the phenomena which takes place in this experiment. Asks Franklin's opinion of his theory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777; A.L.S. 3p.; Chaulnes, Duc de
    Urged by one of his friends to recommend to Franklin, de Neuville, a French officer who desires to fight in the army of the insurgents; has a high opinion of the gentleman's bravery, but considers a recommendation of this kind indiscreet and useless.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; Mem. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Proposal for sending weekly packet boats to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.]; L.S. 1p.; Coder, -----
    Proposes to furnish uniforms for the American troops. Describes and gives cost of each article, which compares favorably with similar articles supplied to the French troops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.]; L.S. 1p.; Coder, -----
    Reports on the clothing and equipment proposed for the American troops. Recommends a certain type of uniform and makes several suggestions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.]; A.L. 2p.; Coder, -----
    Urges Franklin to accept his proposals to furnish supplies for the American troops and to send skilled workmen to repair and keep the equipments and clothing in good condition. Observations on the political situation in England as viewed with relation to the colonies in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; L.S. 2p.; Coder, -----
    Claims that the uniforms and clothing, supplied by him for the American troops, are much superior to those previously supplied by others. Requests Dr. Franklin and Deane not to delay their orders, as otherwise he would be at considerable loss.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; A.L.S 2p.; Coder, Henry
    Concerning the advisability of sending the material to America and having the uniforms made there rather than pay such exorbitant prices for them in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; L.S. 1p.; Coder, Henry
    Makes a report to Franklin on the 12,000 rifles which Dubourg and Dalibard propose to furnish to the United States. Approves the model. Suggests a few changes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Before 1780 March; L.S. 3p.; Coder, Henry
    Describes different plans for destroying England's commerce on the sea, making raids on the English coast, seizing the channel islands and forcing England to come to terms with the United States. Submitted his plans to M. de Sartine. Deplores that they were not adopted by the latter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; The Compiler of the book "Affaires de l'Amérique"
    Recommending a young surgeon to the Deputies of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; A.L.S. 1p.; Conway, Françoise-Antoinette-Jeanne Langlois du Bouchet, comtesse de. Paris
    Report of a battle in America, six hundred English lost, and General Washington wounded; desires to know whether her husband and brother arrived in time to aid their friends; reminds him of his promise to tell her the news, whether good or ill.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N.S. 1p.; De Dangeuil, ---------
    Inquires if Dr. Franklin will be able to come to see him as promised.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. in 3d P. 1 p.; de Dangeuil, -----
    Has called to see Dr. Franklin. Was acquainted with him in London in 1768 and a frequent visitor to him and Sir John Pringle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1773 December 2; L. in 3d P. 2p.; d'Arget, -----
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777] Monday; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Before the express leaves for Nantes, desires to know what sum must be paid Captain Bell.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777] Thursday; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Advises that a copy of a contract with M. de Chaumont be sent to Mr. Williams and also to the Secret Committee.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?] Friday; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Sending letters, etc., received that evening from London; congratulating him on their important contents. Appointing a time to see him on business, relating in part to Captain Hynson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Enclosing a letter from Mr. Bingham with news of the safe arrival, at Martinique, of the cargo from Havre.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; Mem. in 3d P. 1p.; Dampierre, -- Lemaire de
    Request to enter the American service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.] Saturday morning; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Wishes to see Franklin, in Paris that morning, as early as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.] Monday; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Inquiring if Dr. Franklin is going to Versailles and if he could give him a place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; Mem. in 3d P. 2p.; Denombe, André François Broche
    Request for himself and his nephew, Jean Baptiste de Belgarée, to enter the American service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; L. 2p.; Donjeux, Antoine de
    Petitions for a military appointment in America, where he intends to settle with his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; A.L.S. 2p.; D'Ornesan, -----. Gascony
    Desires to enter the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Duboccage, Mme
    Thanking Franklin for sending her a poetical work entitled the "Vision of Columbus."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; A.L.S. 2p.; Dubourgneuf, -----. Pont-Croix
    Begs Franklin to procure him a passage to America and the rank of officer in the army there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777?; A.L.S. 4p.; Dumas, Charles-Guillaume-Frédéric
    Introducing M. Michel Rey, bookseller of Amsterdam. Books sent to Franklin; anxious for news of America; prophesies a great future for the country. Admiration for Robertson's histories. (Incomplete.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumont, -----.
    Entrusted by Mr. Sayre with certain letters to be sent by the first two ships bound for America; desires to know when the next ship will sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; Mem. in 3d P. 1p.; Erenatius, Baron. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; A.L.S. 2p.; Ewing, Alexander
    Asks Dr. Franklin's assistance to obtain the release of his ship from Dunkirk.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Faurines, Jean Baptiste Alexandre
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L. 2p.; -----, ------
    Desiring, with several of his friends, to serve in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Fergusson, W. Paris
    Announcing the arrival of an express at Lord Stormont's with news of an American defeat on October 24th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1777]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Sending a new translation of Richard, lent by M. Quétant. Will let him know as soon as his cannon are in prime condition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1777; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Asking Franklin to accept a gift of some story books which may amuse his grandchildren.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [C.1777 May 25]; Mem. 9p.; de Forestier
    Offers his services to the United States if given the rank of Major General; would raise and train a regiment of dragoons in America to serve during the war with England. Describes how they should be armed and equipped.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.]; L. 1p.; Franquelin, -----
    Offering to supply him with all the information concerning their family and their possible relationship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; A.L.S. 3p.; Garanger, Captain
    Was to have sailed as an officer with M. Du Coudray for America. Could not reach Havre in time. Wishes to be included in the list of officers enrolled by M. Du Coudray and be given the means to leave for America without delay.
  - To Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; N. in 3d P. 1 p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Proposes, to Franklin, to send the list of articles which Congress needs to Holland to get the prices thereof for comparison.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Deane., [1777 ?]; A.L. 2 p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Enclosing a warning against a man in Morlaix called Walker. Invitation to dine with him the following day.
  - To Benjamin Franklin, [1777.] Tuesday evening; L. in 3d P. 1 p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Inquiring at what hour he can get Franklin's instructions for Versailles and if the latter could lend him his carriage.
  - To Benjamin Franklin, [1777.] Friday Morning.; A.L. in 3d P. 1 p.; Greenwood, ------. Paris
    Will wait on Franklin to learn if he has any commands as he leaves Paris Sunday.
  - To Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1777]; L. In 3d P. 1 p.; Hennet, ----. Paris
    Offering to supply America with arms.
  - To Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutchinson, James. on board the ship Sally
    Promising to deliver Franklin's dispatches in Philadelphia, or to destroy them, should he fall into the hands of the piratical cruizers of Britain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Kermorvan, Chevalier de
    Asking for news of his brother who was reported to have sailed for America.
  - To Benjamin Franklin, [1777]; A.L.S. 4 p.; Kermorvan, Chevalier de
    Writes from America where he is erecting batteries and fortifying certain points on the coast. Deplores the lack of unity and activity amongst the Americans. Are averse to making any defensive preparations requiring labor until the enemy is upon them. Explains the difficulties he has to contend with; engineering skill not appreciated. Learned with regret of M. de Woedtke's death in Canada. Solicits promotion to the latter's rank so as to have the right to take part in the Councils of War.